1.3, relationship of project, program,
portfolio and operations management.
You will often find in smaller
companies in particular,
many projects are
managed virtually in isolation.
The project managers would
most likely discuss common
dependencies and resourcing,
but little more than that.
Even though some elements of these
projects could be combined and managed
more efficiently, that path just isn't
followed.
However, the projects that are managing
isolation, the project management
processes, tools and
techniques to scrap the PIMBucke
and still gives them a
high probability of success.
What they're missing really
is just that bit of synergy,
a bit of efficiency that can
be gained by combining them.
But as the organisations
grow larger, they begin to
see that their benefits to
begin by grouping projects.
and other related pieces of work together.
For example, they can be managed in a
coordinated way.
Resources can be balanced between the
different projects.
There can be better communications across
projects and clearer oversight by senior
management on the whole landscape of
projects and how they're progressing.
So what are the alternatives for managing
multiple projects then?
As it turns out, there are three main
ones.
Option one is simply to continue managing
and isolation.
Each project is treated
as a separate stand-alone
project with minimal
information interchange.
Note that an extremely large project is
called a mega project.
The Pinball Guide defines a mega project
as one that is expected to cost $1 billion
US or more, effect one million or more
people, and run for years.
But I would advise remembering that
definition because it's new to the PIMBOC
as good chance that they're going to test
us on it.
Now option number two is to collect
related projects together into a program.
For example a large mining company might
create a program of information technology
projects, a second program
for mine site construction
projects and a third program
for mining operations projects.
The PIMBOC guide defines a program as a
group of related projects, subsidiary
programs and program activities
managed in a coordinated way to
obtain benefits not available
from managing them individually.
They become the option number three,
which is the highest level if you like.
It's a collection of unrelated projects
under a portfolio.
In the mining example, the company could
combine the information technology
program, the construction program,
the mining program, plus other projects
and even some operations work into a
portfolio.
The PIMBOC guide defines a portfolio as
projects, programs, subsidiary portfolios
and operations manage as a group to
achieve strategic objectives.
So just remind you, a program is a
collection of related projects,
a portfolio is generally a collection of
unrelated projects or on related programs,
and key for the exam, remember,
it can include some operations as well.
The PINBull Guide says
program management and portfolio
management differ from
project management in their level.
life cycles, activities, objectives,
focus and benefits.
However, portfolios, programmes,
projects and operations often engage with
the same stakeholders and
may need the same resources
which may result in a
conflict in the organisation.
This type of situation increases the need
for coordination within the organisation
through the use of portfolio
programme and project
management to achieve a
workable balance in the organisation.
If we have a look at Figure 1-3 from the
PIMBOC guide, it illustrates a sample
portfolio structure indicating
relationships between the programs,
projects, shared resources and
stakeholders.
You can see in this diagram that within
the portfolio, Project 1 is not part of a
program, however, it is still managed
within the portfolio to obtain benefits
not available by managing it is a
standalone project.
Project 2 and Project 3 have been combined
to form Program A.
Project 4 and Project 5 have been combined
to form Program B1.
Project 8 and Project 9 have been combined
with some operations
work to form Program C.
Program B2 and Project 6 have been
combined to form Program B.
Project 7 and Program C have been combined
to form Portfolio A.
And everything has been combined to form
the sample portfolio.
I believe it's actually an error in this
diagram.
Yes, the PIMBock Guide can make mistakes.
I believe that Program C is actually a
portfolio.
Why do I say that?
Well, remember the definitions.
The PIMBock Guide defines a program as a
group with related projects, subsidiary
programs, and program activities managed
in a coordinated manner to obtain benefits
not available for managing them
individually.
And a portfolio is projects, programs,
subsidiary portfolios and operations
managed as a group to achieve strategic
objectives.
These tell us that a portfolio, not a
program, can include operational work.
But Program C on the diagram includes
operations, which means
it is really a portfolio.
But anyway, grouping the projects together
in this way makes it easier to enforce
robust governance and introduce
efficiencies and cross-project balancing
and prioritisation based
on risk, funding and other
considerations they would not
otherwise have been possible.
But this structure gives us the big
picture view.
Looking at project program and portfolio
management from an
organisational perspective.
Program and project management focuses on
doing programs and projects the right way
and portfolio management focuses on doing
the right programs and projects.
And that could be an examination question,
so.
Program management.
This is defined as the application of
knowledge, skills and principles to a
program to achieve the program objectives
and to obtain benefits and control not
available by managing program components
individually.
The PIMBOC guide says on page 14.
A program component refers to projects and
other programs within a program.
Project management focuses on
interdependencies within a project to
determine the optimal approach for
managing a project, the optimal approach.
Program management focuses on the
interdependencies between projects and
between projects and
program level to determine
the optimal approach for managing them.
Actions related to these program and
project level interdependencies may
include aligning with your organizational
or strategic direction that to fix program
and project goals and objectives,
allocating the program scope into program
components, managing
interdependencies among the
components of the program
to best serve the program.
That's moving around funding, balancing
out the human resources between the
projects, trying to control the
interdependencies between them,
maybe moving projects around so that there's
less focus on some interdependencies.
Managing project risks may impact multiple
projects in the program and that can be a
big saving if you have a number of
projects facing the same fairly major risk
but it's too expensive to deal with for a
single project and you realize we can deal
with this risk for all of these projects
now it's worthwhile going ahead with it.
Resolving constraints and conflicts that
affect multiple projects within a program.
And as to recover later,
a constraint is anything
that reduces your ability
to manage the project.
Resolving issues between component
projects and the program level,
managing change requests within a shared
governance framework, allocating budgets
across multiple projects within the
program which gives you an enormous amount
of control and assuring benefits realized
from the program and component projects.
So you still have to be able to identify
the expected benefits at the start and
then check at the end or
sometime after the project that's
finished to make sure those
benefits were actually achieved.
An example of a program is the development
of a new online training course,
the development of a web-based learning
management system to host and manage the
course and the development
of back-end financial systems
to manage payment and
financial accounting for the course.
Portfolio management.
A portfolio is defined as projects,
program, subsidiary portfolios and
operations managed as a group to achieve
strategic objectives.
The PIMBOC guide says on page 15 that
portfolio management is defined as the
centralised management of one or more
portfolios to achieve strategic objectives.
The programs or projects
of the portfolio may not
necessarily be interdependent
or directly related.
The aim of portfolio management is to
guide organizational investment decisions,
select the optimal mix of programs and
projects to meet strategic objectives,
provide decision-making transparency,
prioritise team and physical resource
allocation, increase the likelihood of
realising the desired return on
investment, centralise the management of
the aggregate risk profile of all
components and the aggregate means just
combined together or added up together.
Portfolio management also
confirms that the portfolio is
consistent and aligned with
organizational strategies.
Sometimes it's possible to have a project
on your organization, perhaps a small one
or a bit of work, it doesn't
actually align with your
strategy and so something
you shouldn't be doing.
Being in isolation, it can be missed out,
but once you get into a portfolio and you
have people looking at the entire
portfolio, it is much easier to spot
something like that and basically to weed
it out.
Maximizing the value of
the portfolio requires careful
examination of the components
that comprise the portfolio.
As you remember, the components are the
project, bits of operation work,
subsidiary projects and programs and other
portfolios, so a whole mix.
But the component could be any one of
those.
Components are prioritised so that those
contributing the most to the
organisation's strategic objectives have
the required financial team and physical
resources and that reminds me of actually
managing a project or you have some
activities on the critical path and if any
one of those activities is held up then
it's going to slow the entire project it's
going to hold the entire project up and so
what you start to do is you identify those
particular critical activities and then
start putting more time, more people,
more resources into them.
And so now we're taking that up to the
portfolio level.
Instead of looking at individual
activities, you're looking at maybe
programs, other portfolios, pieces of
work, subsidiary projects, rather,
and then seeing which ones are
contributing the greatest or alternatively
which ones are holding the
company back the most, and
you can start putting a lot
more resources into those.
For example, an infrastructure
organisation that has a strategic
objective of maximising
returns on investments may put
together a portfolio that
includes a mix of projects in oil and
gas, power, water,
roads, rail and airports.
From this mix, the organisation may choose
to manage related
projects as one portfolio.
All of the power projects may be grouped
under a power portfolio.
similarly, or the water projects grouped
under the water portfolio.
However, when the organization has
projects in designing and constructing a
power plant and then operates
the power plant to generate
energy, these related projects
can be grouped in one program.
This, the power program and similar water
program become integral components of the
portfolio of the infrastructure
organization.
4.
Operations Management You will find this
on page 16 of the Pimbach Guide and this
is an area that is really
outside the scope of form of
project management as
described in the PIMBock Guide.
Operations Management
is concerned with the
ongoing production of
goods and or services.
It's the business as usual.
It ensures that business
operations continue efficiently by
using the optimal resources
needed to meet customer demands.
It's concerned with managing processes
that transform inputs, for example,
materials, components, energy and labour
into outputs, e.g.
products, goods and or services.
Number 5.
Operations and Project Management Changes
in business or organisational operations
may be the focus of a project,
specifically when there are substantial
changes to business operations as a result
of a new product or service delivery.
Ongoing operations are outside of the
scope of a project, however, there are
intersecting points where the two areas
cross.
Projects can intersect with operations in
various points during the product
lifecycle, such as when developing a new
product, upgrading a product or expanding
outputs, when improving operations or the
product development process, or at the end
of the project lifecycle, and at each
close-out phase.
At each point, deliverables and knowledge
are transferred between the project and
operations for implementation of the
delivered work.
This implementation occurs through a
touch.
transfer of project resources
or knowledge to operations or
through a transfer of operational
resources to the project.
For example when I'm managing an
information technology project and we
create a software package at one stage we
will hand over various deliverables to the
operations team and so they can get them
up and running and by the end of the
project we will have handed over all all
of those products, operations will be used
them and we will provide a manual and
instructions or perhaps training to enable
the support team to be able to maintain
those operations in use.
And that brings us to the end of
relationship of project, program,
portfolio and operations management.
The next lesson is components of the
PIMBOC guide.
Please read the corresponding chapter in
the PIMBOC guide
before watching the video.
Thank you.